なんば　むった
(南波六太)＜兄とは常に 弟の先を
行かねばならない＞
A big brother should always stay ahead of his little brother.
ひびと
＜しかし 弟･日々人が
栄光の宇宙飛行士になった頃➡
However,
while my younger brother, Hibito, became an astronaut,
わたくし
兄の私 六太は 悲劇の無職に…＞
his older brother, Mutta, was tragically unemployed.
＜そんな中 思い出した
幼い日の約束＞
Mu, are you okay? Mom told me that you lost your job.
Hibito
If you haven't found a new job yet,
Mu, are you okay? Mom told me that you lost your job.
That's when I recalled the promise we made when we were kids.
If you haven't found a new job yet,
Mu, are you okay? Mom told me that you lost your job.
you should listen to the tape you recorded on July 9, 2006.
Hibito
俺らは２人で
宇宙飛行士になるぞ｡
(南波日々人)うん｡
We'll become astronauts.
Yep.
＜そう 俺は…➡
Yeah,
I...
宇宙へ行きたい！＞
want to go to space!
ナサ
＜アメリカのＮＡＳＡで行われた
私達の最終試験｡➡
Our final exam was held at a NASA facility in America.
その合格発表を待つ中
日々人は ついに宇宙へ！＞
As we waited for the results to be announced,
Hibito was preparing to go into space.
(ｽﾋﾟｰｶｰ:ｱﾅｳﾝｽ)リフトオフ！
Liftoff.
あずま
(吾妻)打ち上げ成功 おめでとう｡
Congratulations on a successful launch.
《日々人…俺もブライアンの
言う通りだと思ってるよ…｡➡
Hibito,
I agree with Brian.
お前なら きっと 誰よりも…➡
Your first step
最初の一歩は 軽やかだろう》
will be lighter than anyone else's.
Seven Days
Space Brothers
Before my uneasiness
was the end
of my happiness
I came to you
and we were one
Hello Hello
Let's fly
Here in this world we dream
and keep on dancing
Here among light and shadow
we keep changing
so that the wind doesn't let up
Even though the future is vague and unreliable
we are
not alone
#33 Moon Rabbit
There's something I've always wanted to know.
《ずっと
知りたかった事がある…》
How will I react when I see Hibito land on the moon?
《私は日々人の月面着陸を
どんな顔して見るのだろうか》
Will I smile gleefully?
《うれしくて思わず
笑ってしまうだろうか…》
《それとも…感極まって
泣いてしまうのだろうか…》
Or...
Will I be moved to tears?
Which will it be?
《どっちかな…》
Houston here.
みやた
[TV](宮田)こちらヒューストン｡
ミヤタです｡
This is Miyata...
あっ 宮田さん｡
Oh, Miyata.
ヒビトにメッセージが届いたから
転送する｡➡
I have a message to relay to you, Hibito.
ムッタからのビデオメールだ｡
着陸前に見といた方がいい｡
It's a video message from Mutta.
You should watch it before you land.
(ピピピピ ピピピピ…)
(ｱﾗｰﾑの声)４時です！４時です！
4 AM! 4 AM!
4 AM. Aloha.
４時～ アロハ～
《2026年３月８日 午前４時頃…➡
March 8, 2026, 4:00 AM.
私の人生で…あ いや…➡
A defining moment in my life...
No,
a defining moment in Japanese history.
おそらく 歴史上 最も…》
The moment a new record was set for simultaneously ringing alarms.
(父)《日本中で目覚まし時計が
鳴り響いた朝だろう》
4 AM.
It's morning...
《自分の声で
自らを起こそうとする妻》
My wife tries to wake herself up.
Her voice sounds louder than normal.
《いつもより その声は大きく…》
(母)あ～ばばばばば…！
And it's getting annoying!
《そして しつこい！》
(母)あばばばば…‼うう～！
《まあ 当然だ》
Well, I can't blame her.
Live Broadcast of Moon Landing
Your regular programming has been canceled,
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)
この時間は
通常の番組をお休みして➡
月面着陸 生中継特番を
お送りしています｡
as we spend the next hour to broadcast the moon landing.
《これから 私達の息子 日々人が
月に立つんだからな…》
Our son Hibito is about
to step on the moon.
Astronaut Nanba Hibito approaches the moon in the command module Orion.
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)
司令船オリオンで月に
近づいている南波日々人飛行士｡
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)乗組員達は すでに➡
The crew has already moved to the lunar module Altair.
離着陸専用の宇宙船
アルタイルへ移動しています｡
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)
通称 クイーンと呼ばれている
着陸船 アルタイルは➡
The lunar lander Altair, also known as Queen,
will separate from command module Orion momentarily.
まもなく 司令船オリオンを
切り離します｡
司令船オリオン 分離完了｡
(通信:管制官)ＯＫだ｡➡
Command module Orion away.
Okay.
クイーン 確認できた｡
We have confirmation from Queen.
(ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)しばしの別れだ
オリオンちゃん…｡➡
It's farewell for now, Orion.
帰りに また会おう！
We'll see you on the trip home.
It's time for the landing.
(管制官)さあ いよいよ着陸だ｡
みんな集中しろ｡
Stay focused.
せんい
クイーン 降下遷移軌道に入る｡➡
Queen entering descent trajectory.
減速噴射 開始｡
Engaging reverse thrust.
ランディングレーダ 起動｡➡
Landing radar activated.
Updating data in the computer.
コンピュータのデータを
更新する｡➡
1,500 meters, and descending.
高度1500メートルを通過｡
手動操作に切り替える｡
Switching to manual control.
We're counting on you, Hibito.
頼んだぞ ヒビト｡
了解｡
Roger.
着陸点を確認した｡
電力供給ユニットも見える｡
I have visual of landing site.
Power generator is also in sight.
(通信:ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)ギブソンのカメラを
リモートで起動する｡
Remotely activating the camera on Gibson.
よし クイーンの姿をとらえた｡
All right,
we can see Queen now.
100 meters until we reach the surface.
[TV]月面着陸まで あと100メートル｡
80 meters.
[TV]８０メートル…｡
(母)日々人…｡
Hibito...
[TV]６０メートル…｡
60 meters.
[TV]４０メートル…｡
40 meters.
２０メートル…｡
20 meters.
１０メートル…｡
10 meters.
５メートル…➡
5 meters.
４…➡
4.
３…➡
3.
２…➡
2.
1.
１…｡
(日々人･ﾌﾚﾃﾞｨ)はぁ…｡
(ﾊﾞﾃﾞｨ)ばぁ！フフッ｡
着地完了！
We have landed!
よ～し！
やった～！
Yes!
Great job!
Bro!
(ｼﾞｮﾆｰ)兄さ～ん‼
⦅うわっ！⦆
⦅うわぁ～‼⦆
⦅俺 月に行くよ⦆
I can make it to the moon.
⦅では 質問をどうぞ⦆
⦅はい！⦆
Come ask your question.
Yes!
H-Hey...
⦅こんにちは！
南波日々人です‼⦆
Hello!
I'm Nanba Hibito!
I'm definitely gonna become an astronaut!
⦅僕 絶対
宇宙飛行士になります‼⦆
セス
[TV]ＣＥＳ－５１クルー
月に到着です！
The CES-51 crew has landed on the moon!
やった～～！やった！やった！
よし‼
He did it!
He really did it!
やった！やったやったやった！
He did it! He did it! He did it! He did it!
There's something I've always wanted to know.
《ずっと
知りたかった事がある…》
When Hibito stepped onto the moon,
《日々人が月に降りた時➡
私の顔は
笑っているだろうか…➡
would I be smiling?
Or would I be crying?
それとも
泣いているだろうか…➡
I finally have my answer...
それが どっちか 今わかった…》
《両方だ…》
Both.
July 20, 1969.
Apollo 11 lands on the moon.
Neil Armstrong and Buzz Aldrin become the first humans to walk on the moon.
＜二ール･アームストロングと
バズ･オルドリンが➡
人類として初めて
月面に降り立った＞
"That's one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind."
＜これは一人の人間にとっては
小さな一歩だが➡
人類にとっては
偉大な飛躍である…＞
Neil Armstrong.
Yes, it's finally happened.
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)
そう そしていよいよ…➡
The Japanese have always had strong feelings toward the moon.
古くから月に想いをはせてきた
我々 日本人の魂が➡
ようやく月面の土に
大きな一歩を残すのです｡
And now, we've finally left our footprint on its surface...
Thanks to the astronaut Nanba Hibito.
[TV](ｷｬｽﾀｰ)
南波日々人飛行士によって｡
Camera's rolling, Hibito.
(ﾊﾞﾃﾞｨ)もう撮ってるぞ ヒビト｡➡
ちゃんと日本に流れてるかな｡
うまく撮れよ バディ｡➡
Are they seeing this in Japan?
Try to get a good shot, Buddy.
This footage will be a permanent fixture in Japan's archives.
日本にとっては
永久保存版の映像だからな｡
(ﾊﾞﾃﾞｨ)まかせとけ！
I got this.
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)こっちもＯＫだ ヒビト！
かっこよく降りろよ！
We're ready, Hibito.
Make it look good!
かっこいいハシゴの降り方って
あんの？
How do you look good when you're descending a ladder?
I can try jumping like Aldrin.
じゃあ オルドリンみたいに
跳んでみるかな｡
《足が軽い…肩も軽い》
No weight on my legs...
No weight on my shoulders.
No weight on my chest.
《胸も軽い》
あ 宮田さん｡
Oh, Miyata.
It's a video message from Mutta.
[TV](宮田)
ムッタからのビデオメールだ
ヒビト｡➡
You should watch it before you land.
これは見ておいた方がいい｡
月に立つ前に｡
Huh?
(ﾘﾝﾀﾞ)あっ カワイイ！
He's so adorable.
[TV]ウホンッ え～
調子はどうかね？日々人君｡➡
Ahem.
How are you doing, Hibito?
え 何？すこぶる快調？
へっ そういうと思ってたぜ｡➡
What's that?
You're fantastic?
Heh, I knew you would say that.
さぞ宇宙を
満喫していることだろうな｡
You're probably enjoying space.
顔 出さね～んなら
ビデオの意味ね～だろ｡
Why send a video message if you aren't going to show your face?
You've been thrust into the important role of being the first Japanese person on the moon.
[TV]日本人初の月面到達者となる
重要な役どころだが➡
But you don't seem to be feeling any pressure.
そこんとこ お前はたいして
ﾌﾟﾚｯｼｬｰにも感じていないだろう｡➡
However,
だが 吾妻さんより先に
降りていいんだろうかという➡
you might be a little concerned about stepping on the moon before Azuma.
プレッシャーはあるかもしれん｡
[TV]え～ そこで朗報…
あ～ コラッ！アポ！コラッ！➡
But I have some good news...
Hey, wait!
Apo, come back!
I told you to sit still!
もう じっとしとけつっただろ！
[TV](アポ)ワン！ワン！
[TV]え～ そこで朗報です｡➡
So, I have some good news.
After speaking with Azuma's wife,
俺が 吾妻さんの奥さんから
聞いた話によると➡
吾妻さんは 日々人の第一歩を
とても楽しみにしてて➡
it sounds like he's looking forward to your landing.
He even said, "Hibito's probably the best person for the job."
｢日々人こそ 日本の第一歩に
ふさわしい男かもしれない｣➡
と つぶやいていたそうだ｡
[TV]
そういう訳だが 日々人 あくまで
｢かもしれない｣だからな｡➡
There you go, Hibito...
This is pure speculation.
Don't get too cocky.
図にのるなよ｡
ワン！
Hey, wait... Apo, you're too close!
あ～ ちょっと コラ！
アポ 近い！うわっ！
Back off!
Well, in any case, Hibito...
現在
⦅まあ あれだ 日々人…➡
When you take that first step, there's nothing for you to worry about.
とりあえずこれで 何も気にせず
最初の一歩が踏めるじゃね～か⦆
Okay!
《よし！》
Whoa...
《おおっ！何コレ!?》
What's this?
≪おおっ！≫
≪おお～っ！≫
《カラダ軽りぃ！》
I feel so light!
≪おお～っ！≫
The first step Hibito took
＜この時 日々人の一歩が
生み出したもの…＞
＜その１つは
ムーンジャンプという言葉＞
gave birth to the moon jump.
Hibito's first step was plastered across American newspapers as the highest jump in history.
＜月面で最も高く跳んだ男として
日々人の第一歩は➡
アメリカの新聞でも
一面を大きく賑わせた＞
お客さん 今日の見た？
あの日々人のムーンジャンプ｡
So did you see Hibito's moon jump on TV?
あ～見たね｡
(運転手)重たい宇宙服 着てて
あれだよ｡
Yeah, I did.
And those space suits are heavy things.
あいつ 俺の弟だ｡
He's my little brother.
Oh...
《あ～日本の報道が心配だ➡
I'm worried about the Japanese media.
ムーンジャンプ程度で
すんでればいいが➡
I hope his moon jump is all they'll pick up.
あの時 日々人は
もう１つの言葉を生んだ｡➡
Hibito said something else, too.
日本の見出しは きっと…》
The Japanese headlines will be all over that...
⦅月面を踏んでの第一声？⦆
My first words after stepping on the moon?
[ｹｲﾀｲ](新聞記者)
⦅はい そうです｡第一声を必ず
大見出しにしますから はい⦆
Yes, that's right.
Everyone will be paying close attention to what you say in that moment.
⦅ですから ぜひ何か 素敵な
お言葉を お願いしますね⦆
So please prepare something inspirational.
りょうかい
⦅了解です⦆
Got it.
＜…と 新聞社などから 前もって
言われていた日々人＞
Thus,
Hibito was warned by the media beforehand.
Are you really supposed to plan ahead for these things?
⦅そ～いうのって前もって
考えとくもんなのかね～⦆
いちまつ
＜この時 私は一抹の不安を
抱いていた＞
That was when I started getting worried.
＜この男に ちゃんとした
言葉なんて残せるのだろうか＞
Does this guy know how to say anything inspirational?
⦅ほれ 書けるぜ⦆
See? I can write them.
ばら
ゆううつ
にいがた
＜私が｢薔薇｣と｢憂鬱｣と｢新潟｣を
マスターした事を自慢した時＞
Rose
Melancholy
Niigata
When I bragged about learning how to write rose, melancholy, and Niigata...
⦅ふふっ⦆
⦅ふふ～⦆
⦅ひらがなで い～じゃん⦆
Why not use hiragana?
⦅ああ…！⦆
＜と言い放った
このいい加減な男に＞
And that's how lazy he is.
＜結局 日々人は
何も わかっていなかった…➡
It turns out that Hibito didn't understand
自分の第一声が日本の言葉として
世に残るという事の重大さを＞
how his words would end up representing Japan around the world.
Wait, really?
ええっマジで!?
もう新聞出てんの！
The newspaper's already out?
あ～それで見出しは？…まさか｡
So what's the headline?
Don't tell me it's...
ちゃ～んと載ってるわよ
ドーンと！日々人の言葉！
They quoted Hibito, front and center!
《あ～やっぱり…最悪だ》
I knew it...
This sucks.
あれほど 言ったのに…｡
We warned him multiple times...
なすだ
(茄子田)何 何？ん？ん？
Oh, what? What?
Hmm? Hmm? Hmm?
あっは～やっちゃったねぇ～｡
Ah, now he's done it...
Yay!!
Astronaut Nanba Hibito
becomes the first Japanese
person on the moon!!
《何これ…体…重っ》
I don't get it.
My body feels so heavy...
March 8, 2026.
The Altair "Queen" lands on the moon.
＜南波日々人が日本人として
初めて月面に降り立った＞
Nanba Hibito becomes the first Japanese person
to walk on the moon.
"Yay!!"
Nanba Hibito.
When I get back to Japan, I'm going to be known as "Yay's big brother"...
《日本に帰ったら｢イェ～｣の
兄って呼ばれんだろうなぁ》
⦅ハハハ！おおお！アハハハ！⦆
＜日々人はあの後 嬉しさのあまり
何度も跳びはねた＞
Hibito was so happy, he kept jumping up and down.
＜日本のおっさんコメンテーター
がテレビで言った＞
A Japanese commentator made the following remark...
⦅うお～おっイェ～！⦆
Yay!!
[TV](ｺﾒﾝﾃｰﾀｰ)
⦅月のウサギは彼だったん
ですね～ハハハ⦆
"It appears that he was our moon rabbit."
My right hand spent its days afraid of losing something
but wished to be held by my left hand
I lead you by the hand
Is my hand only there to hold my own hand now?
I can't lose it
Amidst my nagging disappointment that I can do nothing
I felt I wanted to do something
I let go again
I'm not alone in this world
If my hands can only hold two things
then I hope one of them is you
Not alone, not alone
I want our hearts to be connected
I want to be connected
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#34 Pug and Hug on a Moonlit Night
＜イェ～！＞
Yay!!
＜ん？
今 あそこで光ったの 何だ？＞
Huh? I thought I saw a flash.
What?
ユーフォー
(ﾊﾞﾃﾞｨ)＜ん？ＵＦＯか!?＞
A UFO?
I never imagined looking at the moon and knowing my little brother was there.
＜弟がいる月を眺める日が
来るなんてな＞
Listen to me, Apo...
＜いいか？アポ
お前は幸運を呼ぶ犬｡➡
You're my lucky dog.
５日後の俺の合格発表も頼むぜ｡
…な～んて言っていたら➡
I need you to help me get selected!
But then I used my luck on something totally pointless!
私は ささいな事に
運を使いまくってしまう＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Pug and Hug on a Moonlit Night"
I'm wasting all my luck!
＜俺の運レベルが
消費されている！＞
パンパカパーン！
今週の宇宙写真です｡
This Week's Space Photo
Living with pets on the space station?
This week's space photo!
うひょ～！
Whee!